# Debangshu Banerjee

Email: bdebangshu@iisc.ac.in LinkedIn: debangshub GitHub: Debangshu93

Google Scholar ID: FXkrG54AAAAJ

## ABOUT ME

I am currently pursuing my doctoral dissertation under the guidance of Dr. Aditya Gopalan at the Indian Institute of Science. I am interested in the intersection of theory and practice of data-driven automated learning models in the field of AGI. Currently I am working on the allignment problem of LLMs with human preferences. At the begining of my dissertation program I had delved in depth in the field of structured and unstructured bandit problems and Markov Decision Processes. Before this I had done my Masters specializing in reinforcement learning and had done a stint at an Bengaluru based AI start-up.

## SKILLS

Programming Languages: python, C

Deep Learning Frameworks: Pytorch, Tensorflow LLM Frameworks: HuggingFace-Transformers RL Frameworks: HuggingFace-TRL, RLLib

Distributed Systems: Accelerate

## EDUCATION

### PhD, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India

2019,-Present

Advisor : Aditya Gopalan

• Department Of Electrical Communications and Engineering

## M Tech, Indian Institute of Science, Bangalore, India

2016-2018

Advisor: Shalabh hatnagar

• Department Of Computer Science and Automation

• Thesis: Hex and Neurodynamic Programming (https://arxiv.org/pdf/2008.06359.pdf)

#### B Tech, Jadavpur University, Kolkata, India

2012-2016

Advisor : Ujjaini Sarkar

• Department Of Chemical Engineering

### Industry Experience

#### WORKING EXPERIENCE

### AI Engineer, AlphaICs Corp., Bengaluru

2018-2019

- Inference on Proprietary Edge Device: Worked with the AI and Compiler teams to implement native versions of deep learning models related to vision, including INCEPTION-V3, RESNET-50 and VGG-NET for proprietary 16-bit integer edge device processor (RAP-E). I was entrusted with training quantized versions of these networks to demonstrate inference for securing funding. Final versions had a test accuracy of 90%. Programming Platforms: C, Python, TensorFlow
- Tensorflow XLA-Framework library development: Developed TeensorFlow XLA Libraries and Optimization for proprietary processor RAP-C. Software development and testing was done by working with AI and Compiler Teams. The results were improvements in speed and memory usage for most internal benchmarks. Developed Runtime Libraries and Optimization for RAP-Processor.

Programming Platforms: Assembly, C, TensorFlow

#### Internship Experience

#### Research Intern, IBM Research Lab., Bengaluru

Summer 2023

• Reinforcement Learning for Constrained Process Modelling: Use Reinforcement Learning Techniques to solve optimal control problems in the industrial production pipeline. Specifically, we explored novel algorithmic and theoretical ideas that could mitigate typical problems in such settings, such as the presence of limited real data and the absence of a reliable simulator (hence offline).

Programming Platforms: Pytorch

## Conference Publications

[1] **D. Banerjee**, A. Ghosh, S. Ray Chowdhury, and A. Gopalan, "Exploration in linear bandits with rich action sets and its implications for inference", in *Proceedings of The 26th International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Statistics*, F. Ruiz, J. Dy, and J.-W. van de Meent, Eds., ser. Proceedings of Machine Learning Research, vol. 206, PMLR, 25–27 Apr 2023, pp. 8233–8262.

## TECHNICAL REPORTS

- 1. **D. Banerjee** and A. Gopalan, "Bad Values but Good Behavior: Learning Highly Misspecified Bandits and MDPs", 2023. (Currently under review)
  - Summary Most practical problems which can be represented as a bandit learning problem inherently assume a model. Previous works have shown that when true bandits deviate from the assumed model structure, popular algorithms like LinUCB and  $\epsilon$ -greedy can suffer a linear regret in the worst case. In this study, we systematically characterize a class of bandit problems which, even though misspecified, will suffer no extra linear regret. This also opens the possibility to designing intelligent features with low model complexity.
- 2. **D. Banerjee** and A. Gopalan, "On the minimax regret for linear bandits in a wide variety of action spaces", *arXiv* preprint arXiv:2301.03597, 2023.
  - **Summary** Minimax regret in bandits is an important field of study in Bandit Literature. Most results focus on either the standard hypercube or the standard sphere as the decision set. In this study, we show a technique to expand the analysis to any  $L^p$  ball, where  $1 \le p < \infty$ .
- 3. **D. Banerjee**, "Hex and Neurodynammic Programming", arXiv preprint arXiv:2008.06359,, 2017. Summary The projected Bellman error (PBE) has been shown to be a more stable objective function to optimize in reinforcement learning literature. This study extends the standard PBE error minimization algorithms like GTD and TDC to include multi-step look aheads. We compare and contrast various hyperparameters and standard RL algorithms in the game of HEX.

Programming Platform: Theano

## Projects

- 1. Towards Reliable Alignment: Uncertainty Aware RLHF, (ongoing)
  - **Summary** How reliable are learned reward models? As our experiments show, they might not be so reliable as to use them for aligning LLMs. We propose an uncertainty-aware methodology for fine-tuning LLMs, which enjoy *low-risk low-reward* properties compared to existing methods.
  - $\label{programming} {\it Platform: {\bf Pytorch, Hugging Face-Transformers, Hugging Face-TRL}}$
- 2. Deep Reinforcement Learning based on Human Feedback, 2023
  Worked in a group to construct demos for the tutorial "Do you prefer learning from preferences" at Neurips 2023.
  Programming Platform: Pytorch
- 3. Deep Reinforcement Learning based on Human Feedback, 2023
  Worked in a group to construct demos for the tutorial "Do you prefer learning from preferences" at Neurips 2023.
  Programming Platform: Pytorch

4. Deep Reinforcement Learning Tutorial, 2022

Conducted tutorials on concepts and implementation of deep RL techniques like DQN, TRPO, PPO, SAC, DDPG for students.

Programming Platform: Pytorch

- 5. On Randomized Least Squares Value Iteration for Misspecified MDPs, 2021 Summary Thompson Sampling is known for its ease of computability in the Bandit Literature. RLSVI is a natural extension of Thompson Sampling in MDPs. However, the study of RLSVI has mostly been restricted to finite state-action space domains in RL. Most attempts to analyze parameterized versions of RLSVI involves unrealistic model assumptions. In this work we analyze RLSVI without any model assumption. We recover the expected  $\sqrt{T}$  term along with the usual linear term associated with model misspecification.
- 6. How Reliable are Test Numbers for Revealing the COVID-19 Ground Truth, 2021 Data visualization for COVID project (Data Handling). See https://arxiv.org/pdf/2004.12782.pdf

## ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

• Stochastic Systems Lab, IISc Advisor: Shalabh Bhatnagar 2017-2018

• Learning Optimization Control and Automation (LOCA), IISc

2019-present

Advisor : Aditya Gopalan

#### TEACHING

•	Teaching Assistant at NPTEL	Fall 2022, 2021
	Concentration Inequalities	
•	Teaching Assistant at Indian Institute of Science	Fall 2023, 2022
	Random Processes (E2 2020)	

• Teaching Assistant at Indian Instite of Science Online Prediction and Learning (E1 245) Fall 2020

## Talks/Presentations

•	EECS Students Symposium, IISc, Bengaluru Student Speaker	2024
•	AISTATS, Valencia, Spain Poster Presentation	2023
•	IBM Day@IISC, Bengaluru, India Student Speaker	2022
•	IISc WorkShop on Deep Reinforcement Learning, Bengaluru, India Student Speaker https://sml.csa.iisc.ac.in/drlworkshop/	2021

## Extracurricular Activities

• Technical Program Committee SPCOM, 2024	2024
• Web and Publication Team SPCOM, 2024	2024
• Student Volunteer COLT, 2023	2023
• Student Volunteer	2022

- Webmaster at https://ai.iisc.ac.in/ General Website maintenace and content update
- Reviewer for various conferences including Neurips, ICML, ICLR, AAAI, AISTATS

## TECHNICAL COURSES

- Analysis
- Real Analysis
- Complex Analysis
- Measure Theory
- Functional Analysis
- Distribution Theory
- Probability
- Probability Theory
- High Dimensional Statistics
- Detection and Estimation
- Concentration Inequalities
- Stochastic Processes and Queuing Theory
- Optimization
- Computational Methods of Optimization
- Convex Optimization
- Linear and Non Linear Optimization
- Geometry
- Multivariable Calculus
- Calculus on Manifolds
- Differentiable Manifolds
- Other Mathematical Topics
- Information Theory
- Game Theory
- Matrix Theory
- Discrete Mathematics

## • Computer Science

- Data Structures
- Algorithms
- High Performance Computing
- ML/AI
- Machine Learning
- Reinforcement Learning
- Topics in AI
- Practical Data Science
- Advanced Robotics Learnning and Control
- Online Prediction and Learning